<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="bp-Best_Practices">
  <title>Best Practices</title>
  <para>This chapter discusses Best Practices related to  Mobicents
  Sip Servlets usage in real world deployments.</para>
  <section id="bp-Best_Practices_Perf_Tips">
    <title>Mobicents Sip Servlets Performance Tips</title>
    <para>Because the default profile of Mobicents Sip Servlets  is targeted at a
    development environment,  some tuning is required to make the server performance  suitable for a  production environment.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Tuning JBoss</title>
      <para>To ensure the server is finely tuned for a production envirionment, certain configuration must be changed.  Visit the   <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JBossASTuningSliming">JBoss Application Server Tuning</ulink> wiki page to learn about optimization techniques.
       </para>
      <para>While it is preferrable to have a fast Application Server,  most of the information doesn&apos;t apply to Mobicents.  In summary, the most important optimization technique is to remove logs, leaving only what is required.</para>
      <para> Check the log configuration file in
      the following location and review the information.</para>
      <para><filename>$JBOSS_HOME/server/default/conf/jboss-log4j.xml</filename></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tuning Mobicents Sip Servlets</title>
<!--Issue #838 Editor Comment - consider using a <variablelist> here.  You can put headings such as "Congestion Control" in the <term> element, and describe the tuning recommendations in a <listitem><para> element.-->      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Congestion Control</emphasis> : It is recommended that this feature is enabled to avoid overload of the server and that the <emphasis>sipMessageQueueSize</emphasis> and <emphasis>memoryThreshold</emphasis> parameters are tuned according to <xref linkend="sscacc-MSS_Concurrency_and_Congestion_Control"/></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Concurrency</emphasis> :
          <emphasis>Default Value : None.</emphasis>  For better performance, it is recommended to leave  this value set to <userinput>None</userinput>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tuning The JAIN SIP Stack</title>
      <para>The stack can be fine-tuned by altering the SIP stack properties, defined in the external properties file specified by the <emphasis>sipStackPropertiesFile</emphasis> attribute as described in <xref linkend="bsssc-binary-SIP_Servlets_Server-Adding_SIP_Connectors"/>.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>gov.nist.javax.sip.THREAD_POOL_SIZE</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Default value: 64</emphasis> </para>
          <para>This thread pool is
          responsible for parsing SIP messages received from socket messages into
          objects.  </para>
          <para>A smaller value will make the stack less responsive, since
          new messages have to wait in a queue for free threads. In UDP, this
          can lead to more retransmissions. </para>
          <para>Large thread pool sizes result in allocating resources
          that are otherwise not required.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>gov.nist.javax.sip.REENTRANT_LISTENER</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Default value: true</emphasis> </para>
          <para>This flag indicates whether the
          SIP stack listener is executed by a single thread, or concurrently
          by the threads that parse the messages. </para>
          <para>Mobicents Sip
          Servlets expects this flag to be set to <userinput>true</userinput>, therefore do not change the value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>gov.nist.javax.sip.LOG_MESSAGE_CONTENT</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Default value: true</emphasis></para>
          <para>Set the parameter to  <userinput>false</userinput> to disable message logging.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>gov.nist.javax.sip.TRACE_LEVEL=0</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Default value: true</emphasis>. </para>
          <para>Set the parameter to <userinput>false</userinput> to disable JAIN SIP stack logging.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The full list of JAIN SIP stack properties is available from
      <ulink url="http://snad.ncsl.nist.gov/proj/iptel/jain-sip-1.2/javadoc/javax/sip/SipStack.html">the SIP Stack Properties Home Page</ulink>
      and the full list of implementation specific properties are available
      from the <ulink url="http://snad.ncsl.nist.gov/proj/iptel/jain-sip-1.2/javadoc/gov/nist/javax/sip/SipStackImpl.html">SIP Stack Implementation Home Page</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tuning The JVM</title>
      <para>The following tuning information applies to Sun JDK 1.6, however  the information should also apply
      to Sun JDK 1.5.  </para>
      <note>
        <para>For more information on performance, refer to  the <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/performance/reference/whitepapers/6_performance.html">Performance White Paper</ulink>.</para>
      </note>
      <para>To pass arguments to the JVM, change
      <filename>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.conf</filename> (Linux) or <filename>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.bat</filename> (Windows).</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Garbage Collection</emphasis> </para>
          <para>JVM
          ergonomics automatically attempt to select the best garbage collector. The
          default behaviour is to select the throughput collector, however a disadvantage of the throughput collector is that it can have long pauses times, which
          ultimately blocks  JVM processing. </para>
          <para>For low-load implementations, consider using  the incremental, low-pause, garbage collector
          (activated by specifying <emphasis>
              <userinput>-XX:+UseConcMarkSweepGC -XX:+CMSIncrementalMode</userinput>
            </emphasis>). Many SIP applications can benefit from this garbage collector type because  it reduces the retransmission amount. </para>
          <para>For more
          information please read: <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/technologies/hotspot/gc/gc_tuning_6.html">Garbage Collector Tuning </ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Heap</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Size</emphasis> </para>
          <para>Heap size is an important consideration for
          garbage collection. Having an unnecessarily large heap can stop the JVM for
          seconds, to perform garbage collection. </para>
          <para>Small heap sizes are not
          recommended either, because they put unnecessary pressure on the  garbage
          collection system.  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tuning The Operating System</title>
      <para>The following tuning information is provided for Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) servers that are running high-load configurations.   The tuning information  should also apply to other Linux distributions.</para>
      <para>After you have configured RHEL with the tuning information, you must restart the operating system.   You should see improvements in I/O response times. With SIP, the
      performance improvement can be as high as  20%. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Large Memory Pages</emphasis> </para>
          <para>Setting large memory pages
          can reduce CPU utilization by up to  5%. </para>
          <para>Ensure that  the option
          <emphasis>
              <userinput>-XX:+UseLargePages</userinput>
            </emphasis> is passed and ensure that the following Java
          HotSpot(TM) Server VM warning does not occur:</para>
          <para><literal>Failed to reserve shared memory (errno = 22)&quot; when starting JBoss.</literal> It means that the number of pages at OS level is still not enough.</para>
          <para>To learn
          more about large memory pages, and how to configure them, refer to 
          <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/technologies/hotspot/largememory.jsp">Java Support for Large Memory Pages</ulink> and <ulink url="http://andrigoss.blogspot.com/2008/02/jvm-performance-tuning.html">Andrig's Miller blog post</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Network buffers</emphasis> </para>
          <para>You can
          increase the network buffers size by adding the following lines to
          your <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><userinput>net.core.rmem_max = 16777216</userinput></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><userinput>net.core.wmem_max = 16777216</userinput></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><userinput>net.ipv4.tcp_rmem = 4096 87380 16777216</userinput></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><userinput>net.ipv4.tcp_wmem = 4096 65536 16777216</userinput></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><userinput>net.core.netdev_max_backlog = 300000</userinput></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para>Execute the following command to set the network interface address:</para>
          <para><command>sudo ifconfig [eth0] txqueuelen 1000 # </command></para>
          <para>Replace [eth0] with the correct name of the
          actual network interface you are setting up.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="bp-Best_Practices_NAT">
    <title>NAT Traversal</title>
    <para>In a production environment,  it is common to see SIP and Media
    data passing through different kinds of Network Address Translation (NAT)  to reach the
    required endpoints. Because NAT Traversal is a complex topic, refer to the following information to help determine the most effective method to handle NAT issues.</para>
    <section>
      <title>STUN</title>
      <para>STUN (Session Traversal Utilities for NAT) is not generally
      considered a viable solution for enterprises because STUN cannot be used
      with symmetric NATs. </para>
      <para>Most enterprise-grade
      firewalls are symmetric, therefore STUN support must be provided  in the SIP Clients themselves.  
      </para>
      <para>Most of the proxy and media gateways installed by VoIP providers 
      recognize the public IP address the packets have originated from.   When both SIP end points are behind a NAT, they can act as
      gateways to clients behind NAT.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TURN</title>
      <para>TURN (Traversal Using Relay NAT) is an IETF standard, which
      implements media relays for SIP end-points. The standard overcomes the problems of
      clients behind symmetric NATs which cannot rely on STUN to solve NAT
      traversal. </para>
      <para>TURN connects clients behind a NAT to a single peer, providing the same protection offered by symmetric NATs and
      firewalls. The TURN server acts as a relay; any data received is
      forwarded. </para>
      <para>This type of implementation is not ideal. It assumes the clients
      have a trust relationship with a TURN server,  and a request session
      allocation based on shared credentials. </para>
      <para>This can result in scalability issues,
      and requires changes in the SIP clients.  It is also impossible to determine
      when a direct, or TURN, connection is appropriate.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ICE</title>
      <para>ICE (Interactive Connection Establishment) leverages both
      STUN and TURN to solve the NAT traversal issues.</para>
      <para>It allows devices to
      probe for multiple paths of communication, by attempting to use different
      port numbers and STUN techniques. If ICE support is present in both
      devices, it is quite possible that the devices can initiate and maintain communication
      end-to-end, without any intermediary media relay.</para>
      <para>Additionally, ICE can
      detect cases where direct communication is impossible and automatically initiate  fall-back to a media relay. </para>
      <para>ICE is not currently in  widespread  use in SIP devices, because ICE capability must be embedded within 
      the SIP devices. </para>
      <para>Depending
      on the negotiated connection, a  reINVITE may be required during a session, which adds more
      load to the SIP network and more latency to the call. </para>
      <para>If the
      initiating ICE client attempts to call a non-ICE client, then the call
      setup-process will revert to a conventional SIP call requiring NAT
      traversal to be solved by other means.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Other Approaches</title>
<!--Issue #838 Editor comment - After reading this section, I got the impression that STUN, TURN, and ICE are not recommended solutions.  

So if these are not the right methods, what should a user be configuring?  

Can you link to other sections in the guide that can show the reader what they should be considering?-->      <para>Other approaches include using proxy and media that can act as
      gateways, Session Border Controllers, enhanced Firewall with Application
      Layer Gateway (ALG) and Tunnelling.<!--Issue #838 Editor Comment - is there more information available on some websites that the reader can refer to?--></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
