<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section id="stf-Seam_Telco_Framework">
    <title>Seam Telco Framework</title>
      <para>The Seam Telco Framework (STF) is a telecommunications application framework based on the JSR-289 specification, and JBoss Seam.  The framework plugs the SIP Servlets 1.1 stack and the Media Server Control API into new or existing JBoss Seam applications.  This allows Seam components to implement both the Web and telecommunication logic of the applications.</para>
      <para>The primary goals of the STF are to: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Unify Web, SIP, and media telecommunication applications.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Allow complex enterprise applications to be built using the same programming model.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Keep logical associations between SIP, Media and Web sessions.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>From an integration perspective, JBoss Seam provides access to different frameworks.  These frameworks are made available to the telecommunication-specific applications for a particular role using the same context.  The STF manages SipServletRequests and Media Server events while utilising existing JBoss Seam framework benefits, including:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Bijection</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Inversion of Control (IoC)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Interceptors</para></listitem> 
        <listitem><para>Scoping</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Transaction management</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>Other advantages associated with the STF include:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Enterprise Java Beans (EJB) and Plain Old Java Objects (POJO) support.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Loosely-coupled, asynchronous telecommunicaton component support.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Web-layer interaction support.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Synchronous and asynchronous light-weight message passing using @Observer-annotated methods.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Integration with existing Seam IDE tools and infrastructure syntax.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>More information about the STF can be found on the <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/mobicents-public/web/seam-telco-framework-for-sip-servlets">STF homepage</ulink>.  For information about JBoss Seam, refer to the <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.com/seam/latest/reference/en-US/html/index.html">community documentation</ulink>.</para>
  </section>