<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<section id="mipbx-Media_Support">
  <title>Media Support</title>
  <para>Mobicents SIP Servlets by implementing the SIP Servlets 1.1
  specification is providing natively support for applications to setup calls
  through SIP Support.</para>
  <para>But since most Telco services have the need for managing and
  controlling media, by example to play announcements, mixing calls, recognize
  DTMF, ... Mobicents SIP Servlets allows applications to control media in 2
  ways.</para>
  <section>
    <title>JSR 309 : Media Server Control API</title>
    <para>This Specification is a protocol agnostic API for Media Server
    Control. It provides a portable interface to create media rich
    applications with IVR, Conferencing, Speech Recognition, and similar
    features.</para>
    <para>Mobicents Media Server provides an implementation of the JSR 309
    specification (currently in public review) using the MGCP protocol to
    allow controlling any Media Server (located in the same Virtual Machine or
    on a remote server) supporting MGCP.</para>
    <para>It is better demonstrated in the <ulink url="http://www.mobicents.org/mss-jsr309-demo.html">JSR 309 example application</ulink> provided with Mobicents SIP Servlets on JBoss 5</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Mobicents Media Server Control API (MSC API)</title>
    <para>Since JSR 309 is not final yet, the Mobicents Media Server provides
    it&apos;s own client API so that any applications within Mobicents SIP Servlets
    can interact with the Mobicents Media Server. One limitation with this API
    is that you can only control the Media Server if it&apos;s located in the same
    JVM as the Mobicents SIP Servlets container.</para>
    <para>The documentation of the API is provided <ulink url="http://hudson.jboss.org/hudson/job/MobicentsBooks/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/media/index.html#captms-MMS_Control_API">in the Mobicents Media Server user guide</ulink></para>
    <para>The following examples demonstrate its usage :</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.mobicents.org/media-demo.html">Media Example</ulink> : a SIP Servlet application showing how to use media
        capabilities (Media playback, Text to Speech with FreeTTS and DTMF
        detection).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.mobicents.org/conference-demo.html">Conference Demo</ulink> : a Conference Media Server demo application built on GWT
        with server-push updates.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.mobicents.org/shopping-demo.html">Shopping Example</ulink> : a Converged JEE Application showing SEAM
        integration, JEE, Media integration with TTS and DTMF support.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
