<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- chapter id nickname: sscacc -->
<section id="sscacc-MSS_Concurrency_and_Congestion_Control">
  <title>Concurrency and Congestion Control</title>

  <para>Concurrency and Congestion control refer to settings you can tune that
  define the way in which messages are processed under heavy load. Needless to
  say, such configurable settings become highly-important in production
  environments. Tuning the concurrency control mode changes the way in which
  the SIP Servlets Server processes messages. Tuning the congestion control
  parameter means increasing or decreasing the point at which the server
  begins rejecting new requests. Both of these parameters can be set in one of
  four different ways: through the SIP Servlets Management Console; by editing
  the server's <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration file; from the
  <literal>dispatcher</literal> MBean; or from the Embedded Jopr integrated
  management platform.</para>

  <formalpara>
    <title>Concurrency Control</title>

    <para>Although the JSR 289 expert group could not agree on a concurrency
    control mechanism for JSR 289, leaving the details up to individual
    implementors, we believe that concurrency control as implemented in the
    Mobicents SIP Servlets Servers provides a highly-useful feature necessary
    in production environments. Concurrency control is implemented in both
    Mobicents Sip Servlets for JBoss and Mobicents Sip Servlets for Tomcat as
    a configurable mode which defines the way in which the SIP Servlets Server
    processes messages. There are a total of three different modes to choose
    from, based upon the individual requirements of your setup:</para>
  </formalpara>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>None</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>All SIP messages are processed as soon as possible in a thread
        from the global thread pool. Note that when using the
        <literal>None</literal> concurrency control mode, two messages
        belonging to the same <literal>SipSession</literal> can be processed
        simultaneously, so you must take measures to ensure that access to a
        shared resource such as the session attribute is synchronized in a
        thread-safe manner.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>SipSession</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>SIP messages are processed as soon as possible except that two
        messages from the same <literal>SipSession</literal> are guaranteed
        never to be processed simultaneously. Messages from the same
        <literal>SipSession</literal> are processed sequentially in their
        order-of-arrival. However, two (or more) messages from different
        <literal>SipSession</literal>s in the same
        <literal>SipApplicationSession</literal> may be processed
        simultaneously, in which case you should take measures to ensure
        shared resource synchronization. You should also pay special attention
        to Back-to-Back User Agent (B2BUA) cases in which each leg of the
        B2BUA consists of a different <literal>SipSession</literal> in the
        same <literal>SipApplicationSession</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>SipApplicationSession</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>SIP messages are processed as soon as possible with the
        guarantee that no two messages from the same
        <literal>SipSession</literal> <emphasis>or</emphasis> from the same
        <literal>SipApplicationSession</literal> will ever be processed
        simultaneously: they are instead processed sequentially in their
        order-of-arrival. This mode is the most thread-safe. However, you must
        still be careful if you are accessing shared resources in an unmanaged
        way, such as by accessing a <literal>SipSession</literal> attribute
        from an unmanaged thread, or from an Enterprise JavaBean. If you do
        so, be aware that such access will not be synchronized.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <formalpara>
    <title>Congestion Control</title>

    <para>Mobicents Sip Servlets currently defines two different congestion
    control mechanisms :</para>
  </formalpara>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>All SIP messages which cannot be processed immediately are put
      into a queue, and therein wait for either a free thread or for the lock
      on their session to be released. The exact size of this SIP message
      queue is a tunable parameter, and it currently defaults to
      <literal>1500</literal>. If the SIP Message queue becomes full, the
      container immediately begins rejecting any new SIP requests with either
      SIP error code 503 until the server catches up or drop any incoming
      messages depending of the congestion control policy chosen until the
      queue is once again diminished.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>If the percentage of memory currently used by the container goes
      over a configurable threshold (90% per default), the container will
      start rejecting any new SIP requests with either SIP error code 503
      until the server catches up or drop any incoming messages depending of
      the congestion control policy chosen until the percentage of memory used
      by the container goes back below the threshold.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Note that either situation, only new SIP requests are rejected; SIP
  responses which arrive in the milieu of a full queue are appropriately
  stored and are processed eventually.</para>

  <para>A background task is running at regular intervals within Mobicents Sip
  Servlets to gather information about the current server congestion and the
  interval can be adjusted in the configuration. This background task can be
  stopped and congestion control deactivated by setting the interval to 0 or a
  negative value.</para>

  <para>Also the congestion control policy, what to do with an incoming
  message when the server is overloaded, is configurable and the possible
  values are :</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>DropMessage - drop any incoming message</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>ErrorResponse - send a 503 - Service Unavailable response to any
      incoming request (Default).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <formalpara id="sscacc-Configuring_the_Concurrency_and_Congestion_Control_Settings">
    <title>Configuring the Concurrency and Congestion Control Settings</title>

    <para>The concurrency and congestion control settings can be configured
    through the SIP Servlets Management Console, by editing the server's
    <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration file, from the
    <literal>dispatcher</literal> MBean, or from the Embedded Jopr integrated
    management platform. Instructions for each method are given below.</para>
  </formalpara>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Tuning Parameters with the SIP Servlets Management Console</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The easiest way to configure the <guilabel>SIP Message Queue
        Size</guilabel> and <guilabel>Concurrency Control Mode</guilabel>
        tunable parameters is to open the <literal>SIP Servlets Management
        Console</literal> in your browser (by going to <ulink
        url="http://localhost:8080/sip-servlets-management"></ulink>), making
        your changes, and then <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>ing them. Note that
        configuring the settings in the SIP Servlets Management Console does
        not persist across reboots. To make your settings changes permanent,
        you should edit your server's <filename>server.xml</filename>
        configuration file; instructions for doing so follow.</para>

        <mediaobject id="sscacc-sas-MSSSManagementConsole-ss-ServerSettings-1">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/mss-MSSSManagementConsole-ss-ServerSettings.png"
                       format="PNG" width="440" />
          </imageobject>

          <caption><para>Tuning the concurrency and congestion control
          settings in the SIP Servlets Management Console</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Tuning Parameters Permanently by Editing
      <filename>server.xml</filename></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Alternatively, you can edit your server's
        <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration file, which has the
        benefit of making your chosen settings changes permanent. Instructions
        follow, grouped by the SIP Servlets Server you are running:</para>

        <procedure>
          <title>Tuning Mobicents Sip Servlets for JBoss Server Settings for
          Concurrency and Congestion Control</title>

          <step>
            <para>Open the
            <filename><envar>$JBOSS_HOME</envar>/server/default/deploy/jboss-web.deployer/server.xml</filename>
            configuration file in a text editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the <literal>Service</literal> element and add a
            <literal>concurrencyControlMode</literal> and/or a
            <literal>sipMessageQueueSize</literal> attribute to it.</para>

            <para>The default value of the
            <literal>sipMessageQueueSize</literal> attribute is
            <replaceable>1500</replaceable>, of the congestion control
            checking interval is <emphasis>30000 millisecs (3O
            seconds)</emphasis>, of the default memory threshold is
            <emphasis>90%</emphasis> and the congestion control policy is
            <emphasis>ErrorResponse</emphasis>. Those are the default values
            which are used even if the attribute is not present in
            <filename>server.xml</filename>. You will need to play around with
            this setting for the optimal value, which depends on the hardware
            running your SIP Servlets Server.</para>

            <para>Possible values for the
            <literal>concurrencyControlMode</literal> attribute include:
            <replaceable>None</replaceable>,
            <replaceable>SipSession</replaceable> or
            <replaceable>SipApplicationSession</replaceable>.
            <replaceable>SipSession</replaceable> is the value of this
            attribute when it is not present—and overridden—in
            <filename>server.xml</filename>.</para>

            <example id="sscacc-MSSJ-Permanently_Changing_Tunable_Parameters_by_Editing_server.xml">
              <title>Permanently Changing Tunable Parameters by Editing
              JBoss's server.xml</title>

              <programlisting role="XML">&lt;Service
 name="jboss.web"
 className="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.startup.SipStandardService"
 sipApplicationDispatcherClassName="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.core.SipApplicationDispatcherImpl"
 darConfigurationFileLocation="conf/dars/mobicents-dar.properties"
 concurrencyControlMode="SipApplicationSession"
 sipMessageQueueSize="1600"
 congestionControlCheckingInterval="2000"
 congestionControlPolicy="DropMessage"
 memoryThreshold="80"&gt;</programlisting>
            </example>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <procedure>
          <title>Tuning Mobicents Sip Servlets for Tomcat Server Settings for
          Concurrency and Congestion Control</title>

          <step>
            <para>Open the
            <filename><envar>$CATALINA_HOME</envar>/conf/server.xml</filename>
            configuration file in your text editor.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Find the <literal>Service</literal> element and add a
            <literal>concurrencyControlMode</literal> and/or a
            <literal>sipMessageQueueSize</literal> attribute to it.</para>

            <para>The default value of the
            <literal>sipMessageQueueSize</literal> attribute is
            <replaceable>1500</replaceable>, of the congestion control
            checking interval is <emphasis>30000 millisecs (3O
            seconds)</emphasis>, of the default memory threshold is
            <emphasis>90%</emphasis> and the congestion control policy is
            <emphasis>ErrorResponse</emphasis>. Those are the default values
            which are used even if the attribute is not present in
            <filename>server.xml</filename>. You will need to play around with
            this setting for the optimal value, which depends on the hardware
            running your SIP Servlets Server.</para>

            <para>Possible values for the
            <literal>concurrencyControlMode</literal> attribute include:
            <replaceable>None</replaceable>,
            <replaceable>SipSession</replaceable> or
            <replaceable>SipApplicationSession</replaceable>.
            <replaceable>SipSession</replaceable> is the value of this
            attribute if when it is not present and overridden in
            <filename>server.xml</filename>.</para>

            <example id="sscacc-MSST-Permanently_Changing_Tunable_Parameters_by_Editing_server.xml">
              <title>Permanently Changing Tunable Parameters by Editing
              Tomcat's server.xml</title>

              <programlisting linenumbering="unnumbered" role="XML">&lt;Service
 name="jboss.web"
 className="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.startup.SipStandardService"
 sipApplicationDispatcherClassName="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.core.SipApplicationDispatcherImpl"
 darConfigurationFileLocation="conf/dars/mobicents-dar.properties"
 concurrencyControlMode="SipApplicationSession"
 sipMessageQueueSize="1600"
 congestionControlCheckingInterval="2000"
 congestionControlPolicy="DropMessage"
 memoryThreshold="80"&gt;</programlisting>
            </example>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Tuning Parameters from the dispatcher MBean</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can navigate to the <literal>dispatcher</literal> MBean from
        Mobicents Sip Servlets for JBoss's JMX console. All changes performed
        at run time are effective immediately, but are not persisted across
        reboots (which, if you want to happen, would require editing your
        server's <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration file as well,
        or instead).</para>

        <para>When editing the <literal>dispatcher</literal> MBean from
        Mobicents Sip Servlets for JBoss's JMX console, values allowed for the
        concurrency control mode are <userinput>None</userinput>,
        <userinput>SipSession</userinput> or
        <userinput>SipApplicationSession</userinput>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Tuning Parameters from Enterprise Monitoring and Managent
      Console</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, once you have installed the Enterprise Monitoring and Managenemt console as described in <xref
        linkend="emom-Enterprise-Monitoring-Operations-Management" />, you can
        change the tunable parameters, follow instructions given in <xref linkend="emom-Embedded-Jopr"/> or <xref linkend="emom-Jopr4Production"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
