<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="ss_jslee_interop">
  <title>Sip Servlets - JAIN SLEE Interoperability</title>

  <para>Why implement both specifications ? There is a religion war raging
  between Sip Servlets and JAIN-SLEE and most see them as competing
  specifications/products and try to choose between one or the other.</para>

  <para>Our take at JBoss, the only vendor to implement both technologies, is
  that they don't need to compete since they complete each other very well and
  it has been one of the leitmotiv behind building Mobicents Sip
  Servlets.</para>

  <para>JAIN SLEE is a more complex specification than SIP Servlets, and it
  has been know as heavyweight and with a steep learning curve. However JAIN
  SLEE has standardized a high performing event driven application server, an
  execution environment with a good concurrency model and powerful protocol
  agnostic capabilities thus covering a variety of Telco protocols.</para>

  <para>SIP Servlets on the other is way much simple and easier to get started
  with. Its focus is currently on SIP + HTTP/JEE only and is more of a
  programming model while JAIN SLEE is more of an application environment, a
  platform. The fact that Sip Servlets is focused on SIP+JEE makes it a
  natural fit to build JEE converged applications and way much simpler than
  JAIN SLEE.</para>

  <para>To us it feels like JAIN SLEE and Sip Servlets target different
  audiences, different needs. We wanted to leverage the power of both and make
  them work hand in hand to build an application that could leverage standards
  all the way without resorting to vendor proprietary extensions. <ulink
  url="http://mobicents.googlecode.com/files/deruelle-JSleeSipServletsInteroperability-final.pdf">Our
  "JSLEE and SIP-Servlets Interoperability with Mobicents Communication
  Platform" paper</ulink> describes our approach and the possible different
  approaches we have identified to achieve the goal of interoperability
  between Sip Servlets and JSLEE.</para>

  <para>You can also use our working JSLEE/SIP Servlets interoperability
  example showcasing our approach.</para>
</section>
