<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jopr Integration</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<p>
			<b><i>This page is obsolete : More detailed and better looking installation instructions are available from the <a href="./user_guides/sip_servlets/index.html#d0e6267">Mobicents Sip Servlets User Guide</a></i></b>
		</p>
		<p>
			<b><i>Throughout this page you can click on the images to see them larger.</i></b>
		</p>
		<section name="Description">
			<p>
				Jopr is an enterprise management solution for JBoss middleware projects and other application technologies. 
				This pluggable project provides administration, monitoring, alerting, operational control and configuration 
				in an enterprise setting with fine-grained security and an advanced extension model. 
				It provides support for monitoring base operating system information on six operating systems as well as 
				management of Apache, JBoss Application Server and other related projects.<br/>
			</p>
			<p>
				See the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/jopr">jopr website</a> for more information<br/> or See the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/embjopr">jopr embedded website</a> 
			</p>
			<p>
				This documentation provides information on how to enable the management of Mobicents Sip Servlets Servers through Jopr with our custom Jopr plugin.<br/>
				<b><i>Note that 2 versions of Jopr are available. One embedded which is more targeted to dev environment and the full one more targeted for production envrionment,
				We will showcase both throughout this documentation page</i></b>
			</p>
		</section>	
		<section name="Features">
			<p>
				With the Mobicents Sip Servlet jopr plugin, you can currently see metrics related to your deployed applications and manage the SipApplicationDispatcher which is a central piece in the Mobicents Sip Servlets Architecture since 
				it has the responsibility of dispatching the SIP requests and responses (that is gets from the underlying jain-sip stack) to the deployed Sip Servlets applications.<br/>
			</p>			
			<p>
				On the SipApplicationDispatcher, you can define the Concurrency
			</p>
			<p>			
				<a href="./mss-jopr-concurrency.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-concurrency.png" /></a>
			</p>
			<p>
				and Congestion Control settings
			</p>
			<p>			
				<a href="./mss-jopr-queue.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-queue.png" /></a>
			</p>	
			<p>
				(More information on <a href="./concurrency.html">Mobicents Sip Servlets Concurrency</a> and <a href="./mss-congestion.html">Mobicents Sip Servlets Congestion Control</a>)
				and also you can see graphically the total number of SIP requests/responses processed by the server,
				the number of pending messages to be processed in all queues and the current percentage of memory used by the container.
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href="./mss-jopr-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-metrics.png" /></a>
			</p>
			<p>
				On your deployed applications, you can see http (since your applications can be converged applications) and sip metrics.<br/>
				Regarding the http metrics, you can get the same ones as those provided by the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/community/docs/DOC-12829">Tomcat Jopr plugin</a><br/>
				Regarding the SIP metrics, for each application, be it a pure SIP application, a converged HTTP/SIP application or a SIP application embedded in an EAR, you can see the following metrics :<br/>
				<ul>
					<li>Currently Active Sip Sessions and Sip Application Sessions</li>
            		<li>Maximum number of Active Sip Sessions and Sip Application Sessions</li>
                    <li>Number of sip sessions created for the sipapp and Sip Application Sessions</li>
                    <li>Number of expired sip sessions and Sip Application Sessions</li>
                    <li>Number of sip sessions and Sip Application Sessions rejected</li>
            		<li>Sip Session and Sip Application Sessions Average alive time</li>
					<li>Max Sip Session and Sip Application Sessions alive time</li>
				</ul>	
				<a href="./mss-jopr-session-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-session-metrics.png"/>	</a>			
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Installation Instructions">
			<subsection name="Jopr for Development">
				<p>
					The Embedded Jopr called also JBoss Administration console is available from  <a href="http://mobicents.googlecode.com/files/embedded-jopr-1.1.war">here</a> and works with Mobicents Sip Servlets starting from version 0.7.<br/>
					If you want to install it from the source, follow those instructions :
					<ul>
					<li>Follow the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/community/docs/DOC-12807">Embedded Jopr installation instructions</a> to install the latest version of Embedded Jopr.</li>
		
					<li>Instead of dropping the embedded-jopr.war in $JBOSS_HOME/server/default/ directory, create a directory called embedded-jopr.war in $JBOSS_HOME/server/default/deploy directory and unzip the embedded-jopr.war in it</li>
							
					<li>Get the Mobicents Sip Servlets Jopr Plugin from the source code : <code>svn checkout http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/servers/sip-servlets/jopr-plugin mss-jopr-plugin</code></li>
					
					<li>In mss-jopr-plugin, do a mvn clean install</li>
				
					<li>Then copy the generated <code>jopr-mobicents-sip-servlets-plugin-1.1-SNAPSHOT.jar</code> from the target directory to the <code>$JBOSS_HOME/server/default/deploy/embedded-jopr.war/plugins/</code></li>
				
					<li>Start your JBoss Application Server (you can start it on localhost)</li>
				
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Jopr for Production">
				<p><b>Note that those instructions works equally to install the Mobicents Sip Servlets Jopr plugin for RHQ or JON</b></p>
				<p>
					<ul>
					<li>Follow the <a href="http://jboss.org/community/docs/DOC-12828">jopr installation instructions</a> to install the latest version of jopr. </li>
					
					<li>Stop the jopr server and agent if they are running</li>
					
					<li>Get the Mobicents Sip Servlets Jopr Plugin from the source code : <code>svn checkout http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/servers/sip-servlets/jopr-plugin mss-jopr-plugin</code></li>
					
					<li>In mss-jopr-plugin, do a mvn clean install</li>
				
					<li>Then copy the generated <code>jopr-mobicents-sip-servlets-plugin-1.1-SNAPSHOT.jar</code> in the target directory to the <code>jopr-server-2.1.0.GA/jbossas/server/default/deploy/rhq.ear/rhq-downloads/rhq-plugins/</code></li>
		
					<li>Start the jopr server then the agent</li>
				
					<li>Start your JBoss Application Server in making sure that you specify the binding address when starting such <code>sh run.sh -b 192.168.0.10</code> 
					(the JBoss AS will not get recognized on localhost)</li>								
									
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection>			
		</section>
		<section name="Usage Instructions">
			<subsection name="Jopr for Development">
				<p>
					<ul>
					<li>Log in to the jopr console on <a href="http://localhost:8080/embedded-jopr"/> and login as admin (user=admin, password=admin)</li> 
					
					<li>From the tree on the left side of the screen, under <b>Services</b>, click on <b>MobicentsSipServlets</b> link then click on the <b>jboss.web:type=SipApplicationDispatcher</b> link to see the metrics coming in.</li>
					
					<a href="./mss-embjopr-home.png"><img src="small-mss-embjopr-home.png"/></a>
				
					<li>To get the metrics coming in, you will need to use an example application such as location service by example so that the SipApplicationDispatcher process requests.</li>
					
					<a href="./mss-embjopr-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-embjopr-metrics.png"/>	</a>
					
					<li>To see Metrics about your application, click on your application under <b>Converged SIP/Web Application (SAR/WAR)</b> link.</li>
					
					<a href="./mss-embjopr-applications.png"><img src="small-mss-embjopr-applications.png"/>	</a>
										
					<li>Then select the <b>Metrics</b> tab to actually see the metrics of your application.</li>
					
					<a href="./mss-embjopr-session-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-embjopr-session-metrics.png"/>	</a>
					
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection> 
			<subsection name="Jopr for Production">
			<p><b>Note that those instructions works equally to use the Mobicents Sip Servlets Jopr plugin for RHQ or JON</b></p>
			<p>
				<ul>
				<li>Log in to the jopr console on <a href="http://localhost:7080"/> and from the <b>Dashboard</b> Tab, in the <b>Auto Discovery</b> portlet, import your server (by example <code>deruelle-laptop JBossAS 4.2.3.GA default (192.168.0.12:1099)</code>) from under localhost.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-auto-disc.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-auto-disc.png"/></a>
			
				<li>Then from the Dashboard, in the <b>Recently Added Resources</b> portlet, click on the server,</li> 
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-resources.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-resources.png"/></a>
				
				<li>Then on the new Monitor view click on the <b>JBossWeb Server</b> link</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-monitor.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-monitor.png"/></a>
				
				<li>Then click on the <b>SipApplicationDispatcher</b> link to see the metrics coming in.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-jboss-web.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-jboss-web.png"/></a>
			
				<li>To get the metrics coming in, you will need to use an example application such as location service by example so that the SipApplicationDispatcher process requests.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-metrics.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>To see Metrics about your application, click on the <b>Converged SIP/Web Application (SAR/WAR)</b> link.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-sip-apps.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-sip-apps.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>Then click on your application.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-applications.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-applications.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>You will need to click on the <b>Configure</b> link for the Monitor Tab to select the metric data you want to see</li>
				
				 <a href="./mss-jopr-configure-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-configure-metrics.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>and then select the <b>MetaData</b> tab to actually see the metrics of your application.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-session-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-session-metrics.png"/>	</a>
				
				</ul>
			</p>
			</subsection>			
		</section>				
	</body>
</document>