<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Load Balancer Jopr Integration</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<p>
			<b><i>This page is obsolete : More detailed and better looking installation instructions are available from the <a href="./user_guides/sip_servlets/index.html#d0e5999">Mobicents Sip Servlets User Guide</a></i></b>
		</p>
		<p>
			<b><i>Throughout this page you can click on the images to see them larger.</i></b>
		</p>
		<section name="Description">
			<p>
				Jopr is an enterprise management solution for JBoss middleware projects and other application technologies. 
				This pluggable project provides administration, monitoring, alerting, operational control and configuration 
				in an enterprise setting with fine-grained security and an advanced extension model. 
				It provides support for monitoring base operating system information on six operating systems as well as 
				management of Apache, JBoss Application Server and other related projects.<br/>
			</p>
			<p>
				See the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/jopr">jopr website</a> for more information or See the <a href="http://www.jboss.org/embjopr">jopr embedded website</a> 
			</p>
			<p>
				This documentation provides information on how to enable the management of <a href="./load-balancer.html">Mobicents Load Balancers</a> through Jopr with our custom Jopr plugin.<br/>
				<b><i>Note that 2 versions of Jopr are available. One embedded which is more targeted to dev environment and the full one more targeted for production envrionment,
				We will showcase only the production one since the embedded one only works embedded in JBoss and the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer is independent from the JBoss server.</i></b>
			</p>
		</section>	
		<section name="Features">
			<p>
				With the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer jopr plugin, you can currently see metrics, configure and manage the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer.<br/>
			</p>			
			<p>
				On the Mobicents SIP Load Balancer, see graphically the total number of SIP requests, responses and concurrent calls processed by the load balancer.
			</p>
			<p>			
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-metrics.png" /></a>
			</p>
			<p>
				You can also define the interval between runs of task that removes nodes that expired, set the value which indicates when node has expired and 
				see the list of nodes the Load Balancer can forward SIP messages to. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-config.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-config.png" /></a>				
			</p>
			<p>
				You can also start and stop the load balancer
			</p>
			<p>	
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-ops.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-ops.png" /></a>			
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Installation Instructions">						
				<p><b>Note that those instructions works equally to install the Mobicents Load Balancer Jopr plugin for RHQ or JON</b></p>
				<p>
					<ul>
					<li>Follow the <a href="http://jboss.org/community/docs/DOC-12828">jopr installation instructions</a> to install the latest version of jopr. </li>
					
					<li>Stop the jopr server and agent if they are running</li>
					
					<li>Get the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer Jopr Plugin either from jboss maven repo at 
					<a href="http://repository.jboss.org/maven2/org/mobicents/tools/sip-balancer-jopr-plugin/1.0.BETA1/sip-balancer-jopr-plugin-1.0.BETA1.jar">http://repository.jboss.org/maven2/org/mobicents/tools/sip-balancer-jopr-plugin/1.0.BETA1/sip-balancer-jopr-plugin-1.0.BETA1.jar</a> 
					or from the source code : <code>svn checkout http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/tools/sip-balancer-jopr-plugin</code> and do a <code>mvn clean install</code> in the sip-balancer-jopr-plugin directory</li>
					
					<li>Then copy the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer Jopr Plugin jar in the target directory to the <code>jopr-server-2.1.0.GA/jbossas/server/default/deploy/rhq.ear/rhq-downloads/rhq-plugins/</code></li>
		
					<li>Start the jopr server then the agent</li>
				
					<li>Start your Mobicents Sip Load Balancer as explained <a href="./load-balancer.html">here</a>(and one node that connect to it to see it appear in the list of nodes).
					<b>Note that you will need to either download a <a href="http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2/org/mobicents/tools/sip-balancer/1.0-SNAPSHOT/sip-balancer-1.0-20090115.213906-24-jar-with-dependencies.jar">snapshot version of the Mobicents Sip Load Balancer</a>
					 or install the Load Balancer from the source at <code>http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/tools/sip-balancer</code> because the current released version doesn't expose the different metrics and management operations</b></li>												
									
					</ul>
				</p>			
		</section>
		<section name="Usage Instructions">
			<p><b>Note that those instructions works equally to use the Mobicents Sip Servlets Jopr plugin for RHQ or JON</b></p>
			<p>
				<ul>
				<li>Log in to the jopr console on <a href="http://localhost:7080"/> and from the <b>Dashboard</b> Tab, in the <b>Auto Discovery</b> portlet, import your Mobicents SIP Load Balancer (by example <code>Mobicents SIP Load Balancer 1.0-SNAPSHOT</code>) from under localhost.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-dashboard.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-dashboard.png"/></a>
			
				<li>Then from the Dashboard, in the <b>Recently Added Resources</b> portlet, click on the Mobicents SIP Load Balancer,</li> 
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-dash-added.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-dash-added.png"/></a>
				
				<li>Then on the new Monitor view click on the <b>mobicents:name=LoadBalancer,type=LoadBalancer</b> link</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-monitor.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-monitor.png"/></a>
								
				<li>You can now see the metrics coming in</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-metrics.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-metrics.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>To configure the Load Balancer and see the list of nodes in the cluster it is connected to, click on the <b>Configure</b> Tab.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-config.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-config.png"/>	</a>
				
				<li>To start and stop the Load Balancer, click on the <b>Operations</b> Tab.</li>
				
				<a href="./mss-jopr-lb-ops.png"><img src="small-mss-jopr-lb-ops.png"/>	</a>
									
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>				
	</body>
</document>